<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>jsqr.org</title>
<link>https://jsqr.org/projects.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://jsqr.org/projects.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Johnathan Jenkins&#39; personal website</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Computational Law</title>
  <link>https://jsqr.org/proj/comp-law-course/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<hr>
<section id="background-introduction-to-computational-thinking" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background-introduction-to-computational-thinking">Background: Introduction to Computational Thinking</h2>
<p>MIT offers a course called Introduction to Computational Thinking (6.C25 / 18.C25), which is available <a href="https://computationalthinking.mit.edu">online</a>. Okay—nothing special so far. There are lots of course videos and lecture notes on the web now. What’s more remarkable is that the entire course—lectures and homeworks—is structured around interactive notebooks mixing explanatory text, worked examples, and exercises.</p>
<p>This is a brilliant way to organize a course. And, of course, it’s not entirely new. Wolfram has been sponsoring <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/books/">books</a> that are essentially Mathematica notebook printouts since at least the early 90s. And the idea of a notebook interface borrows from Knuth’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming">literate programming</a>. But somehow bundling everything together in a consistent package on the web makes a difference, inviting engagement and experimentation.</p>
<p>I worked through the Fall 2024 version of the course because I was interested in the core topics (epidemic models, climate science, and the Julia programming language). I wonder, though, if the main thing I took away was enthusiasm for this style of teaching technical information.</p>
</section>
<section id="law-subset-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="law-subset-code">Law <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csubset"> Code</h2>
<p>Running with the thesis that law is like computer code, or that law is a form of ‘code’ in the broader sense, we can imagine what an analogue of the MIT course might look like. Begin with adapting existing coding agents, just to get a sense of the possibilities of working with text in the same way programmers work with computer languages. Then, progress through a sequence of notebooks, demonstrating approaches to increasingly complex legal tasks.</p>
<p>Along the way, we’d need to explore answers to several questions. Programming languages have compilers (or interpreters), linters, type-checkers, assertions, and test suites; how can we adapt those ideas to legal language? What is the equivalent of formal verification for natural language, and is it worth the trouble? How do we handle editing and versioning? Coding agents are currently a bit like REPLs; what’s the right user interface for other modes of development? Is there something like ‘literate programming’ when the object code is itself a contorted form of natural language?</p>
<p>I wouldn’t expect to come up with definitive answers to those questions, which are both difficult and vague, but it is important to adopt a point of view on at least some of them.</p>
</section>
<section id="an-outline-for-an-introduction-to-computational-law" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-outline-for-an-introduction-to-computational-law">An outline for an introduction to computational law</h2>
<p><em>Very much a work in progress.</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Prelude.</strong> Reading on the recent history of neural networks, transformers, and language models. Moving beyond the chatbot: data curation, coding agents &amp; tools. <em>Exercise:</em> develop several <a href="https://agentskills.io">agent skills</a> to aid legal problems. Example: extracting citations from a brief along with a summary of the relevant rule of law.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Using Language Models through an API.</strong> <em>Exercise:</em> set up infrastructure (notebooks, dependency management, API keys) for the rest of the sequence. Practice extracting structured data from text and generating summaries.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Embeddings, classification, and retrieval.</strong> <em>Exercise:</em> implement a classifier for legal clauses in two ways (few-shot prompting and using kNN and embeddings). Implement a retrieval tool for legal texts.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Working with legal texts.</strong> Structural properties of legal texts: outlines, headings, citations, rules, and entities. <em>Exercise:</em> redo the example from first-week exercise (extracting citations and summarizing rules) in computer code.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Evaluation.</strong> Simple metrics and strategies for evaluating classification, retrieval, and quality of generated output. <em>Exercise:</em> characterize (a) classification performance on a simple labeled dataset, (b) retrieval performance, and (c) performance on generating summaries of legal rules.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Logic, law, and automated reasoning.</strong> Classical propositional and predicate logic. Modal logic and defeasible logic. Approaches to automated reasoning. <em>Exercise:</em> try evaluating legal propositions by ‘faking’ formal logic. Where do you draw the line between capturing relevant domain logic (the logic of a legal rule) and falling back on the language model’s sea of background knowledge? Compare results in toy examples to automated reasoning systems like the Z3 SMT solver or Prolog.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tabular data.</strong> Overview of commercial applications. <em>Exercise:</em> build a tabular analysis tool for collections of legal documents, building on the previous exercises.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Ethics &amp; citation-checking.</strong> Ethical considerations in applying AI to the law. Ethics of assistive tools for citations. <em>Exercise:</em> build a system that operates over a corpus of interlinked documents, checking citations to other documents in the corpus and checking that the references actually support the claims, and presenting results for human verification.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Specs &amp; drafting aids.</strong> <em>Exercise:</em> build a tool to aid drafting legal texts. Generated text should be a fragment of a legal document, based on a precedent, satisfying requirements (i.e., checked using a suite of specs or tests), and making claims grounded in cited authorities.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fine-tuning.</strong> Basics of fine-tuning models using <a href="https://axolotl.ai">Axolotl</a> or similar tools. <em>Exercise:</em> reimplement one of the functional elements you’ve built in previous modules (e.g., extracting citations) by fine-tuning a small model. Evaluate task performance as well as resource requirements; can you maintain quality while increasing speed and efficiency on the task?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Orchestration.</strong> Compare approaches to orchestrating AI functions: coding agents and skills, programming frameworks, tools &amp; MCP. <em>Exercise:</em> create a legal agent for working with precedents, specifications, and authorities to produce fragments of legal text to serve as first drafts of a memo.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>projects</category>
  <category>law</category>
  <guid>https://jsqr.org/proj/comp-law-course/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI for legal epidemiology</title>
  <link>https://jsqr.org/proj/legal-epi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<hr>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jsqr.org/proj/legal-epi/Snow-cholera-map.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="250"></p>
<figcaption>Epidemiology starts with data</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="overview" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overview">Overview</h2>
<p>Legal epidemiology – understanding the effects of laws on health – requires an understanding of what the law is. But laws are spread across jurisdictions and different levels of government, and are framed in technical language that can be difficult to encode for analysis. Since 2024, I have been working with collaborators on a project to apply large language models and modern retrieval methods to make encoding of laws easier, focusing on the municipal codes and ordinances of hundreds of citites in the United States. This is part of a broader interest in making law more accessible.</p>
</section>
<section id="timeline" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="timeline">Timeline</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Initial concept presentated to the <a href="https://med.nyu.edu/departments-institutes/population-health/divisions-sections-centers/epidemiology/center-opioid-epidemiology-policy">COEP</a> center at NYU Langone (March 28, 2024)</p></li>
<li><p>Internal presentation with updated <a href="2024-10-07-preso.pdf">slides</a> describing prototypes (Oct.&nbsp;7, 2024).</p></li>
<li><p>Magdalena Cerda et al., <a href="https://www.milbank.org/quarterly/articles/stemming-the-tide-of-the-us-overdose-crisis-how-can-we-leverage-the-power-of-data-science-and-artificial-intelligence/">Stemming the Tide of the US Overdose Crisis: How Can We Leverage the Power of Data Science and Artificial Intelligence?</a>, <em>Milbank Q.</em> 2025; 103(SI):0610 (June 10, 2025).</p></li>
<li><p>Presentation at Society for Epidemiologic Research (SER) <a href="https://epiresearch.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/2025-Participation-List.pdf">Annual Meeting</a> (July 13, 2025).</p></li>
<li><p>NYU <a href="https://wp.nyu.edu/ml4good/">Machine Learning for Good Lab</a> is hosting a Masters’ thesis project related to this project. (Winter 2025—)</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="current-version-of-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-version-of-code">Current version of code</h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/jsqr/legiscope">Legiscope</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="people" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="people">People</h2>
<ul>
<li>Samrachana Adhikari (NYU Langone)</li>
<li>Kimberly Villalobos Carballo (NYU)</li>
<li>Magdalena Cerda (NYU Langone)</li>
<li>Corey Davis (Network for Public Health Law)</li>
<li>Jaskiran Dhinsa (NYU Langone)</li>
<li>Charles DiMaggio (NYU Langone)</li>
<li>Theodore Hill (NYU Langone)</li>
<li>Spruha Joshi (University of Michigan)</li>
<li>Daniel Neill (NYU)</li>
<li>Pooja Shah (NYU Langone)</li>
<li>Utkarsh Srivastava</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>projects</category>
  <category>epidemiology</category>
  <category>law</category>
  <guid>https://jsqr.org/proj/legal-epi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
